[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to the stoa i'm peter limberg
the steward of the stowa
and the stoa is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most
at the knife's edge of this moment and
today we have
james karcz author of finite infinite
game
amongst other amazing books and uh john
verveiki
um who created the awakening from the
meaning crisis and he's spearheading the
deal logos project that
i'm sure everyone here is aware of uh so
these men
need uh no further introduction i'm sure
everyone here knows them
so how today's gonna work uh john and
james
are gonna have a conversation for about
an hour we're gonna just like
geek out and listen and then we're gonna
have a 30 minute kind of q a at the end
so if you have any questions for for
john
or james uh put in the chat box make
sure you have a big queue question
because i think the chat box is going to
be lit today um so that will kind of
flag it for me
so that being said um i'm going to
allow jon to unmute himself uh
and james you gotta unmute yourself
again
there you go yeah right so i'm gonna
mute myself and then
take john in and then you guys can uh go
jam all right
um so i guess uh where i'd like to start
james is uh we we did uh have the
pleasure of uh
meeting each other at a conference uh
which we were talking about just before
and um uh
i would like to sort of pick up maybe
from that as a common point
and uh just quickly review where i'm
coming from and where i'm coming at and
um how i've come to your work and um
what role i see with it within my my
work
and then maybe turn things over to you
so maybe give me like 10 minutes to sort
of riff for a bit
yeah i'd love i'd love to hear it so
uh the work i do as a
sort of science i do as a cognitive
scientist is to work on
a very core problem uh which is a
a a a problem that needs to be solved
because i think it's at the core of
cognition
i think there's a process that is
at the core of our ability to categorize
to communicate to solve problems
um to perform inferences i won't repeat
those arguments
they're available at length and you you
saw a version of them
that the central process is the process
that i call relevance realization
which is the right the ability to zero
in on relevant information
and you're doing that in a way that
avoids either an algorithmic search of
all possible information
which is combinatorial explosive and
impossible or just
merely being arbitrary and just randomly
picking
so somehow we we steer between the skill
and charybdis
of algorithmic totality and
arbitrary you know finitude you know
just a finite
arbitrary partiality is a better way of
putting it and somehow we
we reliably zero in on relevant
information and then some of that
relevant
information enters our conscious
experience and becomes salient to us
etc and i think this is very central to
uh
uh to um cognition and then
the argument is that the way
we sort of do relevance realization
is deeply analogous um to the way
evolution works in that
evolution is a process by which um
there's variation
and then there's selection put on it and
that sort of reconfigures things from
which new variation is generated
selection is put on it and you you get
this sort of accordion
and then a self-organizing system
revolves with change or it evolves and
then the idea is
your brain is doing exactly that your
brain is constantly
introducing variation to maintain
more options for itself it doesn't want
to get locked down into having no
options
so it opens up variations but it also
wants to be efficient in its in its use
of its resources so
it's constantly doing this and so it's
constantly evolving
it's fittedness to the environment and i
use that analogy analogous to biological
the biological fittedness of an organism
and then the and the idea here is that
there is
no definition of fittedness in the sense
that there is no essential features
shared by all all
creatures that are fit you know uh some
are big some are small some are tall
some are short some are hard servers
etc right all that all the only thing
that's required is that they
keep the they keep the process of life
going itself
and so there is no definition
uh to bitterness and one of one of the
part of the genius of darwin is
he gave up the attempt of the
naturalists um you know the the
the in the sense of the uh the clergymen
who were going out trying to
determine the definition of the
perfection of things so they could know
the mind of god instead he gave up
trying to find such an essence and
instead proposed
a universal process by which fittedness
is constantly redefining itself
and restructuring itself and i think
what's relevant
is similarly evolving and constantly
redefining and restructuring itself so
there is no
essence to relevance also i mean what
you find relevant
one minute will not be relevant the next
minute um of all the there's not no
property that all the things you find
relevant share
other than you find them relevant etc
and so i think there is in that sense no
essence and therefore no perfectability
or
and i use this term deliberately final
solution to relevance there isn't a way
of saying it now
we're done it's finished now why this
matters existentially and here's when
i'm taking off my hat as a cognitive
scientist and
putting on a different hat
is that i think for various historical
and structural reasons
and there's i think very ample evidence
for it our current
culture is going through what i've
called the meeting crisis that
people are this is not a dearth of
semantic meaning that's not what i mean
i'm talking about the kind of meaning
that psychologists talk about when they
talk about meaning in life
uh meaning in life is the sense that
your life is worth living
that there is a sense of connectedness
to oneself
and to each other and to the world
that makes the suffering
worthwhile in some fashion
and what's interesting about the
research about that
is that meaning in life in fact is not
primarily about possession
or even a sense of contentedness in fact
subjective well-being are measures of
contentedness and meaning in life can go
in different directions
my primary and good example of this is
having a child
when you have a child all the measures
of subjective well-being go down you're
frustrated you're tired you're hungry
you're uncertain about the blah blah
blah but why do people have children
then well because their meeting in life
goes
up well what is it about that well it
turns out that
it's that sense of connectedness
especially the sense of mattering
the sense of being connected to
something that is beyond
one's egocentrically specific concerns
and what how i put these two together is
the argument
that
meaning in life is about is about the
phenomenological sense
of the connectedness that is actually
what is being constantly
produced by relevance realization i so i
use the bridging term religio to cover
that religious
sense of being connected and we know why
we want to be connected we want to be
connected because
if we aren't connected if we aren't
doing relevance realization and creating
affordances
we're not any kind of cognitive agent
we're going to we're going to suffer a
combinatorial explosion
or we're going to suffer the death of
arbitrary chaotic
cognition and so i think that
human beings have created ways of
engaging in
what i call serious play which might put
two of you turns uh in opposition but
maybe we can negotiate that
what i mean by that is play that they
are willing to deeply commit themselves
to
uh precisely because what they want to
do is
play with and play in that evolution of
the connectedness
precisely because there is no way to
finish it
finalize it uh perfect it and so
i think uh humans have created
many things that whose sole purpose
is to
draw into awareness to give us access
and to accentuate um our sense of
connectedness
and to play with it so that we may
enhance it
you know poetry and music are ways of
just playing
with our relevance realization machinery
but i do think that
what has been lost in our culture
are ways in which human beings
have been guided in how they play so
i'll make one final point and then i'll
turn things over to you
the the that very process by which we
are adaptively
intelligent that self-organizing
that that self-organizing dynamical
coupling
is also the very same process by which
human beings fall into self-deception
so the very relevance realization that
prevents us from
having to check all the information can
also misfire and bias us
and prejudice us in in
important and self-destructive ways so
cultures have perennially
come up with practices that are designed
to try and address and alleviate that
self-deception on one hand
and enhance the religio on another in
some kind of coordinated fashion
and then i think and i've done work on
this we published a consensus paper on
it in psych inquiry
i think the the most common term across
cultures and time for that is wisdom
and i think wisdom is very different
from knowledge i think wisdom is a way
to enhance religio enhance relevance
realization by ameliorating
self-deception
and by affording enhanced senses of
meaning in life
what we've lost historically is we've
lost
a world view and a tradition and a set
of
institutions and guides and practices
for the cultivation of wisdom
so i often do this with people in groups
i'll say where do you go for information
they have a ready answer the internet
uh where do you go for knowledge they'll
still pretty much say science
and then when i say where do you go for
wisdom and there's a deafening silence
and because of that what's happening is
people
often feel very bereft about how
to deal with these perennial problems
that undermine religio
and undermine their capacity for
relevance realization and cognitive
agency and one of the dangers that has
come in our society and you'll see
another connection to your work here
is that we have confused we've confused
propositions
and belief systems with
the very like we've we've reduced
all knowing to merely propositional
knowing
we've lost a sense of these dynamic
processes of
participation and coupling and
involvement
that are actually the home
of meaning making and so what we've
tried to do is we've tried to create
ideological replacements uh
for that i think um and i i saw
something very analogous to
the critique i'm now making in your book
the religious case against belief
that what we try to do is create these
structures that totalize perfect and
complete
um when when what we in fact
what religion is doing is constantly
trying to keep
moving um our response to mystery
the the fact that we can't complete this
it's open-ended
etc and so i think another aspect of the
meeting crisis and this is what peter
does a lot of work on
is that people try to create sort of
pseudo-religious
ideologies and political structures
that attempt
to capture religio
in sets of statements that are designed
to bring about conclusion
what i think is need and what and so the
primary form of discourse is out of
adversarial debate
because the point and here's again your
finite indefinitive games
the point is to defeat the other side
so that there you're now entitled to be
unchallenged
and not have to take up ever again the
problem
um i'm trying to work into
and work with many other people peter
included this environment included
towards a way of interaction
that gives prominence to religio rather
than
credo and that is designed to
get people to come into right
relationship with religio and
continually evolve
their capacities for relevance
realization cultivate wisdom
as opposed to trying to come to some
final conclusion
and so that's where i see your work on
infinite and finite games
uh directly relevant um if we could the
game of discourse
and so i'm thinking of habermas here i
think is a clear example of what you
mean
we often pretend that it's something
that's a necessity but we're always
it's always been constructed by mutual
agreement and the thing is do we want
the game of gift discourse to be finite
games that seek perfection and
completion
and talk in propositional closure
or do we want forms of discourse that
afford that
right that continuing evolution
uh so they they promote a continuity of
contact
with a constantly changing environment
that are constantly
to use your language moving the horizon
of intelligibility
and so that's how i sorry that was me
trying to compress a lot of my
thinking into a very short time and try
to show you connections i see between my
work and your work
john this is a very rich material
you're thinking wait a minute you're not
giving me
you're only giving me an hour not a
semester
if you would take a whole term to uh to
get into this stuff
i mean it's lovely beautiful i love it i
i
i've been doing some work lately um
believe it or not
on economic theory but one of the things
i wanted to do
in that was go back and look at the
intellectual roots of our thinking about
the way we think about
uh money in society and and that that
kind of thing and so i've been reading
i i went back to uh plato and aristotle
and
and um the uh i you know
of course i read them thoroughly in
graduate school
uh some of them in greek even that was a
bit of a job but
you know i did yeah but then um and then
uh read them on and off over the years
but but
now more recently looking at them you
know
any anytime i go back to the greeks i'm
always surprised by finding something
i didn't realize was quite there yeah
you're talking i'm thinking uh when you
talk you talk about uh engagement and
discussion disc
you use the word discourse um
i i was surprised to read in a
commentary
that plato invented discourse
you wouldn't think that right but but i
invented the dialogue
a dialogue never occurred in uh in
in human literature uh before uh before
plato and what happens in a dialogue is
really interesting and very
relevant to what you're talking about
yes i used the word dialectically
but but and but usually translated
dialogue
but i'm going to use the word dielectric
because it it does
it's a slightly different um it gives it
a little more gravity i think
yep i agree um but the but what happens
if you you talk you you make the the
distinction between wisdom and knowledge
in uh in the uh dialogue called uh
theaters socrates runs into this young
a mathematician actually he's a geometer
and uh someone introduces him
and then socrates looks at the young man
he's a young guy
and he sees that he has an ugly face
he's a very ugly young man
but socrates was hugely ugly in himself
famously ugly and so he said i see
we share something in common he said
the young man he starts off that way and
he said i want to see if we
share anything else in common so let's
talk he said what do you
do the man said i'm a g i do geometry he
said
now tell me i i don't know the
difference between
wisdom and knowledge socrates said
and the young man he said can you tell
me what knowledge is
and he said oh yes we we learn this we
learn how to do that
a plumber has a certain degree of
knowledge and so on and socrates says
now wait a minute
you're talking about the use of
knowledge i want to know what knowledge
itself
is and that becomes much more difficult
and of course
unanswerable and then then we begin to
see that the dealer
then actually then he he makes it really
surprising it's a great uh dialogue by
by the way theater fun to go back and
read again
and he says you probably have heard
socrates said
that i was born by way of a midwife
and uh the young man said no i didn't
know that
and he and then socrates makes this
amazing remark
i have taken up the art of midwifery
myself
intellectual midwifery he said i
help people bring ideas into
birth if they're not well conceived they
need someone to help them
on the other hand i can't do it myself
i'm sterile i need you to bring my
wisdom and my knowledge into uh into
birth
and so what he does is establish in the
dialectically the dialectic
an ongoing discussion and we find out at
the end
by the way that this is this is the
the last dialogue socrates has before he
goes
at the end of the dialogue he goes right
into the jury in athens
who condemn him to death about an hour
later after he finishes his dialogue
and um but but that but the dialogue
never ends
that's right and and so what you're so
what you're getting at
is this open-ended conversation that
that goes on
and then i want to add something to that
um
i i i would love to i could spend hours
on this stuff you'll have to slow me
down maybe but but aristotle
aristotle's interesting and he's
different than uh socrates and plato in
a number of ways but in one one
important way
he sees like in the way you're talking
about it
he sees our involvement as human beings
as
profoundly social that is we we are
engaged as human beings
so that that our well-being is
always a well like you use the uh the
example of the family
so you you you can't be happy as an
individual
aristotle's famous uh remark is that the
purpose of life is is is to become happy
you you die monia he called it uh
actually that's a very bad translation
of eudaimonia but
it means something more like well-being
the way you talked about it
yeah and but the the basic insight in
aristotle is that we
are social beings our primary
relationship is to those around us
and therefore all of our knowledge our
wisdom and so on
is is a wisdom is a communal wisdom
knowledge is something we have with each
other not something i have
myself and and with wisdom uh
as well of course it's interesting that
the discussion about what wisdom is
really has never been answered it still
goes on right i mean
plato plato didn't get an answer and we
don't have one either exactly
except what you're getting at is an
ongoing yes
uh the the the the con
wittgenstein uh said
that the meaning of language is not what
it stands for
but what comes of it and
i i want to i want to say the meaning of
a word is what comes of it
and a meaningful life is one that
something comes of
with others i i that's that's my
uh my own personal view and that that i
think is
is is buried in what i've tried to say
in finite and infinite games that
we've got we've got a we are competitive
with each other
but together we are we are in a deeper
kind of ongoing uh
dialectic dialogue community and
and uh and and so on so i'm i'm i'm very
much uh
taken by your your thinking on this i
love the idea of
of um that was a very good distinction
by the way about
uh on the one hand you've got the
algorithm on the other
uh you've got this wide open field and
uh you've either got chaos or you've got
you've got stifling order
and there's some you want to get
somewhere up in the in the middle of
that
balanced and so on and uh that's that's
very good that's very very nice thinking
i'm
i'm very grateful to have that
distinction well thank you
james i'm very you've afforded me lots
um so
i want to respond both to your
aristotelian point and to your socratic
point
i'll respond first to the aristotelian
point uh so part of that of the
the argument that's coming out now from
what's called 4e cognitive science
the idea that cognition is inherently
embodied embedded extended and enacted
um and the work particularly of my
friend greg enriquez
um and the work of dan sperber and
mercier
and others is is this idea of
distributed cognition that most
of our problem solving is not done
as individuals um and ed hutchins made
this uh
did the uh the famous case study of this
he talked about
how a ship is navigated and you have a
bunch of people and you also have all
their instruments
and no one person navigates the ship the
the networking
of the descriptive cognition right the
people and the tools
right yeah what actually navigates the
ship and you can also think of
like you can extend that metaphorically
to the ship and state
et cetera and then the the
idea there is what the research is now
showing is
reasoning let me be clear about how i
want to use
this term um i take rationality to be
much more than the logical management of
inference i take rationality to be any
systematic and reliable
process or procedure uh for addressing
the ways in which we fall into
self-deception
so i think that just like argumentation
can make you rational there's important
ways
in which mindfulness practices can make
your irrational in an intentional
in a in an attentional way so
what is coming out of this is if we
if we if we if we take that sense of
rationality that more comprehensive and
more ancient sense i would argue also
what we
have increasing evidence for is that not
only is most of our cognition done in
distributed cognition
most of it should be done in distributed
cognition because that's where we
that's where we optimally achieve sort
of overcoming self-deception
it's not perfect it can't be that would
be algorithmic but it's much more
reliably
better um so if i'm on my own
i'm liable to fall into confirmation
bias but if i'm talking with you as i am
now
uh that confirmation bias is liable to
be challenged
because if i'm if i'm a tall empathetic
in the conversation
i will take your perspective and that
will get me out of being not
locked in to my own perspective right
right
so i i think that um the fact that
cognition
i often use the metaphor that long
before the internet networked compute
computers together culture networked
brains together embodied brains
people together uh within distributed
cognition
and so i think that's part of the reason
why
i think aristotle said that i think part
of the reason why people
are seeking out these biological
practices
now to respond to your socrates point um
you'd be pleased to know that i'm
actually working on a series called
after socrates
that is about trying to uh recover
the ancient tradition of dialectic from
socrates
you know through the stoics and through
the neoplatonus
and try to unpack what that meant
as a project and what i want to do is
after sort of unpacking that as much as
i can
historically i want to put it into
forgive the pun i want to put it into
dialogue
with all these emerging communities like
this one here
where people are trying to enter into
dialectical relationship again
as a way of understanding it and so one
of the things that
comes out and you said uh theaters and
i'm i'm reading many books around this
topic right now but
one is an excellent book i don't know if
you've read it by gonzalez called
uh dialectic and dialogue and he talks
about
how what plato's doing in the dialogue
and he'll
he shows that socrates often is
like if you if you read it too
superficially it looks like socrates is
just refuting people
but actually there's two types of things
he's constantly steering between
he's steering between the person who
just offers sort of
first-person intuition right right but
he's also
he's also refuting people who often who
offer third person
perspective technical definitions so
that you know
uh when he when you know they're
pursuing courage they got the two
generals
and one gives his intuition and socrates
destroys it of course
and then the other gives his technical
definition he's learned from the sofas
and then socrates destroys that and then
as you pointed out
the dialogue looks like it ends in
emporia but what gonzalez points out is
that
things like courage actually and this is
where i think it links up to what i said
about relevance realization
can't be given any final definition uh a
virtue is ver and this is aristotle's
point as well right virtue is about
steering between the algorithmic and the
arbitrary
in an ongoing developmental fashion
and so what what gonzales argues is that
socrates can't
demonstrate with definition the virtue
but he often exemplifies it
in the actual process of the dialectic
and so he's
so gonzales points out something that
people often miss at the end of that
dialogue
uh both generals are sort of pissed off
of course because they right
but they both say they want their sons
to come and spend time with socrates
oh yeah right right because
right because courage is something in
that sense you have to catch
in dialectic you can't define it and you
can't resolve it through debate
and so part of what i'm interested in
right is this is this interconnection
between
dialectic uh i think you agree it's a
kind of infinite game
steering the virtuous steering between
arbitrary and algorithmic
and this ability to also steer between
you know
first-person immediacy and third-person
objectivity both as sort of authorities
that shut
down conversation in a profound way
and so that and i'm trying to figure out
okay what does that look like what
how does that work and and so very much
i'm trying to figure out
um i i i'm not trying to be socrates
that would be ridiculously hubristic
but i'm trying to understand is there a
way in which we can
bring that system of constraints
into how we're interacting like right
now for example
yeah well i i i hope i do hope i
i think that's that's uh really um
uh you know that's the most fundamental
element of our humanity
yes the the ability you know
socrates said or actually plato said it
but
i think socrates voiced it i'm not sure
which dialogue
uh he pointed out that dialect
dealecticae is the most
unnatural thing we have it's it is
strictly human
yes it's exactly what defines us
as human beings as opposed to animals
yeah
and and and then the other thing is and
you you've been applying this all along
and
in fact you've said it pretty directly
um it doesn't have a goal it doesn't
have an ending
it doesn't have a resolution it keeps
going
and that that means that uh we we have
we have not only an open history but
an open interpretation of what our
history has
been yes and where it should be going
and so we have to look forward and
backward
at the same time at the same kind of
dialectical
analysis and uh so uh
i'm i'm really uh right with you on this
uh on this uh uh on this exercise by the
way
one other thing i loved about i i always
liked about aristotle
he can never decide anything he gets to
the
you know the end he kind of fudges the
ending of everything
he never is he's never absolutely that
makes him infuriating to read but
but uh but on the other hand he keeps
that openness right at the end
no he's not a third person to use your
your election yes i i think that's
correct
um so so james can i ask you a question
then that sort of points to
what we're talking about in your first
book i'm sorry and you're
sorry i don't know it's your second book
but the second book by you i've read
back to the first book i read by you the
one that really got me introduced to you
and actually that's what influenced me
to influence casa to invite you to the
conference
i should tell you a quick story about
this um so i have my son jason he's my
older son he's living with me right now
and i'm trying to get him like out of
sort of a cartesian pursuit of certainty
and you know we have all these ongoing
dialogues and
he's doing all these practices with me
uh etc
but the thing i did the thing i did that
really sort of
loosened him up and set him in motion
and not
totally pleasantly for him it's been
also disruptive but in a really healthy
way
as i gave him your book and he came away
from that and this is what he said
and and take it let me finish it because
i think it's really high praise
he said this is a really great book it's
so disturbing
um because it really
really um really shook him up and which
one the
leaf book the yeah the religious case
against belief because
i think and i think this is a proper way
to put it in the language we're crafting
here together
it had a really huge socratic impact on
him it really
you know you know socrates wisdom begins
in wonder if
that that ability to you know open
things up and call things into question
to set them into motion
but here's here's the question i want to
ask because it's a question that i'm
also exploring
in this project and with other people um
it's a one one critique i have of plato
it's interesting i criticized sort of
plato's
specific content on this but plato
exemplifies the opposite
so let me talk about the second thing
and you mentioned it too and that's why
i want to
start there for me plato is sacred
in the way you just described i can go
back to plato
right i'll get an insight i'll it'll
transform my life transform my life i'll
live a certain way things will unfold i
go back to plato and i see something i
didn't see before
and then this reciprocal opening just
keeps happening again and
again and again and plato's sacred for
me in that sense
because he's a he's an inexhaustible
fount of intelligibility right that
doesn't mean that i don't question him
it doesn't mean that i think he's it's
everything's there
i don't think it's complete but it's
this sense of sacredness as a reciprocal
opening into
the inexhaustible now that's what plato
exemplifies for me but one of my
problems with plato is he seems to have
a notion of the sacred
as the perfect as the unchanging yeah
right yeah yeah and that the point is to
come to
right and so
and i think that that has been woven
into our culture
in a fashion sorry sorry
that has been woven into our culture in
a fashion
that has been very deleterious to us i
think
that notion of sacredness as completion
as perfection as unchangeability
has really in some sense cut us off
from religio very much like the
naturalists before darwin we're trying
to find
the defining definition right of
the perfection of of design and
that that was a doomed project from the
beginning
i think that platonic notion of
perfection has been sown into our
culture in a way that's been
very detrimental to our experience of
religio
and that part of what i see happening
also in
this these so i do a lot of participant
observation i go to these groups
like like peter pops me sorry
i got it don't worry about it it's okay
there hopefully that'll open it okay so
what i see happening
in these dialogical practices is
so peter carr uh no not what's his last
his first name peter anyway carrie in
his book on
augustine's uh invention
[Music]
sorry about this hello
it's 601
sorry somebody trying to deliver
something
i'm sitting next to my phone i'll get a
call too
probably well i only have it turned off
but that's something that's being
delivered for my son so i need to leave
and of course it's being delivered right
now
so anyways yeah go ahead so i'm doing a
lot of participant observation
in a lot of these biological practices
and also reading a lot about them and
talking to a lot of the inventors and
practitioners and promoters
and one of the things that i see
happening is not only
this rediscovery what we're talking
about here
but i see uh so carrie in his book uh
says
he talks about he it's titled
augustine's invention
of the inner self but he says that the
word he wants to use isn't the english
word invention he wants to use the latin
word inventio
that means both to discover and to make
right both
are just to make oh yeah and so what i
see people
doing in these practices these
dialogical practices
i see them in ventio or perhaps
reinventio
sacredness they're transforming
sacredness not from
perfection completion lack of change
but instead this sense of coming into
you know the fount of you know
inexhaustible fount of ongoing
intelligibility
right and so that's why the idea
of emergence is so central now that the
point of the dialogue
is to get emergent meaning rather than
to solidify positions
and so i i'll often uh a a a criterion
not a definition
that i've come up for dialectic is that
you and i together get to a place we
couldn't get to individually
and that that has a taste of sacredness
to it because it gives us an
active sense of the inexhaustible right
so do you think that right
you see i'm making a connection between
your first and second book that
one motive why infinite game play
is becoming more both since both more
needed and more practice
is precisely because it's a way of
people reinventio
this uh what what what sacredness means
and breaking us out
of that aspect of plato that i think has
been detrimental
uh to our our understanding what do you
think of that as a proposal
well let's hope that's the case i
i very much i very much agree with that
uh actually
the the uh my own view of plato is that
the only way you can read plato is to
have read
the neo-platonists first yes
wow james i totally believe that
my gosh that's totally convergent
totally that is yes yes yes yes
so uh and the reason i say
that yeah you know very well what the
what the neoplaton has said is to look
at that
that that platonic idea of the good the
perfect the whole the
truth the light or whatever the hell you
want to call it
lots of different names
uh is that essentially uh to realize
you're not gonna get there
it's it's beyond you uh or as one of the
uh
one of the jewish uh uh the mystics said
the only way you can know god is to be
god
yeah and uh and we we're a long way from
that and
and as a result everything we're doing
is is essentially wrong
i mean we're not there we don't have the
truth the truth is
is uh elusive it's beyond us it's it's
still to be reached and so on
and that's a very important that's why
um it's
the the uh that's why plato's republic
is so interesting because in the
republic
yeah uh if you remember in the uh in the
announce the uh metaphor of the cave
of course the anagogic consent totally
yes
so he's got these these people locked up
in a cave
and one of them gets out and goes out
and sees
the uh the truth but what's really
interesting is
the fellow comes back and tries to get
the others to follow but they won't
[Laughter]
and they were right not to in a way in a
way although
my view is that they should have at
least gone out
to the forecourt of the of the cave or
something you know
yeah but anyway uh that's right no it is
a danger that
that that the possibility of the
absolute yeah
and and uh and we see it you know it
what's interesting also is that that's
one of the ways of misunderstanding the
dialectic
because um the way hegel conceived
was that it had a direction it
ends up somewhere and it ends up right
in plato's
idea of the you know basically the
absolute and uh
and then and marx bought into that at
the
the directionality of the dialectic and
i think that was one of um
his tragic uh flaws anyway uh
the you're right to uh bring that out as
a danger
i'm uh right i'm i agree with that
totally well i just i mean one of the
projects i've been engaging is to try
and
um make uh neoplatonism viable again i
mean i have i've got words of platinus
tattooed on my leg
because i i like it platinus how you
have simultaneous you have this
you know a beautiful synthesis of
argumentation and what
pierre hado called spiritual exercise
the actual process of trying to
you know no you're not just informing
people with argumentation you're trying
to transform their state of
consciousness
right now i'm actually and this is i'm
meeting the person at the end of the
tradition i'm reading
uh demacias you know uh problems in
solutions confirming first principles
and how he you know he calls he calls he
calls
his first principle the ineffable and
that he
places it even beyond uh
yeah yeah yeah and so um
and i mean there's lots of good work
being done about this which brings me
again to a point that was
at the core of uh
the religious case against belief which
is
and this reminds me of uber it reminds
me of from
which is there's a big difference
between you know
being curious and having a problem to
solve
and experiencing wonder in which you
call things into questions so you can
confront mystery
and those are two very different
experience those are two very different
things
both projects are needed for human
beings all right i'm not i'm not
right there's a sense in which you can
read plato as
trying to turn wonder into awe
make it almost reverential um and that's
clearly i mean when you read plato's
seventh letter
that sense of mystery right is so so
profound so i'm wondering then again
if right if what
part of what you could be
interpreted as saying is that the
reinvention of this sacred
as the
as the inexhaustible kind of
intelligibility requires a corresponding
remembrance i'm using remembrance here
in the sense of sati
like mindfulness a deep remembrance
of what from calls the being mode that
mode in which we're trying to enter into
right relationship with mystery
rather than trying to resolve a problem
and bring it to conclusion
that and that that we have to a large
degree
we have forgotten how to do that in a
reliable way
in our culture uh we are locked almost
perpetually in the having mode
the problem-solving mode and what i
think i see you doing in both your books
tell me if this is a fair interpretation
is a kind of deep
existential getting us to deeply
existentially remember
that being mode that mode of coming into
right relationship with mystery and that
and what it takes to do that that i mean
it
i i would argue that it takes practice
it takes a community of practice
in order to do that oh oh oh yeah
yeah no you're absolutely right right on
that one no kidding
yes you know good we're
what can i say but hurrah to them
[Laughter]
well i mean that's it's actually really
wonderful to be able to talk to you in
person directly like
this james because i mean i teach your
work
in you know in my videos and in my
courses
and so it's nice to be able to make sure
that i'm treating you fairly and
appropriately
listen uh you you are for sure
yeah so far uh you you know as i said
um there's uh
there you know there are glacier loads
of
of thinking and knowledge and and
so on behind all these ideas and uh
and it's it's it's it's really worth an
adventure out there
to explore that stuff and that's that's
really what i was uh was thinking when
uh
when i brought up plato and aristotle
yeah uh
totally i mean just just rich very much
stuff
so anyway um yeah this is good now the
the i'm i'm assuming when you use the
word
religio you mean it in the sense of
binding right
of yes yes very very often that
word is is interpretable as yoga
as a yes as it bringing together
as a yoking of different things
uh connecting but at the same time
not resolving not making a complete
circle out of it
but uh but but in other words not not
completely algorithmic
and not completely wide open yep
but very nicely right up the uh
right up the middle as uh yeah
yeah another another element that
um that i found i i find missing in both
plato and aristotle
but but his really ingredient in the
idea of the dialectic
is that is the place of history now now
i mean it this way
uh that most of us think of our history
as
in in what i what i would like to call
calendric
terms a calendar i was born on a certain
day
i went to school there i did this i did
that
and that's my story that's not my story
my story is the civilization
i was born into and and the reason it's
my story is that i'm living the
civilization it's not something that's
descended on me it's something i'm
taking up
and uh one of the ways one of the very
vivid ways
uh we we've been forced to see it is in
racism
i mean we are for example as a nation
historically speaking you know i'm
talking
big history capital h history speaking
not
not calendrical yeah uh we are still a
slave owning nation
enslaving nation and we we never freed
ourselves
we not only did we not free ourselves
from
uh you know not only free the slaves we
haven't freed ourselves from that
that mentality of uh of the slave owner
having a working class uh people you can
store
away in a ghetto or a slum or a prison
or uh you know off the map in a
in a reservation somewhere in a
desperate
desert location so um
i i i want to say that the dialectic
brings
with it a sense of of history in the
sense not only that we have a past
but we're a pet we're living a past yeah
and the living
living the past is also a way of living
a future
and um because we are we're
participating
we're either continuing it as it was
which is probably impossible but
but we're we're also transforming it as
we go along
yes and it gives us uh it it gives the
sense of
meaning a much greater reach
in a way it's not just that i have a
meaningful life
uh with you know within my
calendrical years but but that
that my the meaningfulness of my life
continues through my children through my
students
through my friends through my through my
country
through my countrymen and through my
fellow human beings on and on
uh so i would i would just introduce
that into the uh
into the discussion as uh not not as a
not as a uh critique or no no
no but as but as a continuous
uh contiguous idea i i think that point
is actually confident with the previous
point i think it was plato's commitment
to perfection and unchanging ability
that made him disregard and i think and
i also have critiques of the person i'm
going to introduce now
but i think history in the sense that
you're talking about is very analogous
to like in the sense that heidegger is
often talking about it
um he's talking about it as i i
i often use this metaphor and you can
see how i'm bridging between heidegger
and victoria in this metaphor
that history is the story of our
cultural cognitive grammar
and how right um our cultural cognitive
grammar
what's thinkable for us and what's
doable for us uh
uh has you know it has a history to it
there is a line of progression
um and like you say uh we may make
certain political changes in
in the in the um modern sense of
politics not an
aristotle sense we can make political
changes but that doesn't mean that we've
changed the cultural grammar
the cultural cognitive grammar by which
we think and behave
and so uh you know we're still we still
think you know heidegger's notion that
we treat everything as a standing
reserve
and things are largely objects to be
manipulated
et cetera et cetera and i i agree
and so part of what i did in my series
awakening from the meeting crisis was
try to trace out the history
of that cultural cognitive grammar and
how how much
it is so embedded in us and i think of
your notion of
availing it is so embedded into us that
it's invisible to us because it's
transparent
like the lenses of my glasses are
transparent because precisely because
i'm seeing through them and by means of
them
i don't see them and there's you know
there's a difficult philosophical task
of learning to do this step back and
look at it
rather than automatically unquestionably
no very important
yeah no that's that's absolutely
critical yeah i think
um you know that my uh one of the things
i
argue in this the book i've i've
finished and still
kind of fiddling with is that the first
the first challenge of a teacher is to
get
his or her students to know what they
know
and they know a lot more than they think
they do
and when i've what i've tried in this
book the reason i went back to plato and
aristotle
is that we see the tracks of their
thinking all
over our brains yes yeah they talk
you know we see them all through our
head you know
they thought this stuff up and we're
still thinking it
yeah so so uh the the point is we're
we're thinking the language of the dead
we've been giving
we've been given this language we didn't
make it up this language has been around
for a hell of a long time
and this way of thinking and these these
ideas these concepts
even the grammar we speak and so on it's
very very important
to take those glasses off and look at it
at it
look at what you look at what's going on
in your head
yeah you don't realize it but and then
and then and then plato has this
interesting thing
you probably know his theory of
enemiesis which is uh
the collective knowledge that is we we
there's a there's a knowledge we all
have we
just have to be reminded of it in in a
sense
and and i i that's no one really buys
into that completely but
but on the other hand what he's getting
at i think is that there is a
there's a kind of fundamental of
of knowledge in us that we
that comes through our culture and uh
and we don't we don't see we see through
it
we see with it and uh rather than see
it and so one of the great jobs of a
teacher i think as a writer too
is to get that it out there so you look
at it exactly
see what you're doing so there's a
couple of thinkers that converged on a
way of talking about that after and
metzinger and others
uh they call it a transparency opacity
shift the ability to go from something
being transparent to being
opaque and then uh you you also need to
do the other you need to
sometimes stop looking at certain things
and learn
remember how to look through them again
yeah yeah right
right and so you know and so i i i
sometimes
extend the analogy i say you know i step
back and i look and see if it's
distorting and i do this
right to sort of transform my lenses but
how do i know that i've actually cleaned
them well i have to put them back on and
look through them and see if i can see
differently
again right because and so you have to
constantly go back and forth between the
two
oh oh there's no final cleaning
we're filthy to the end you know
we're all we're all fake in a way yes so
uh
but but uh but but there's they're are
different
qualities of fake fakery after all
but but anyway that i'm glad you brought
that up
very nice point well uh
so i don't know when peter wants to go
either yeah if you want you can open it
yeah absolutely we've been going on here
for an hour
so perfect i'm going to say that the
time flew by
uh james it just grew by it was it it
did didn't it yeah
yeah now this is great fun yeah yeah
so yes perfect timing we're exactly at
the hour uh we have a bunch of great
questions in the chat
um let's go with okay i gotta let
everyone unmute themselves
so everyone can unmute themselves now so
use it wisely
um nicholas if you can be first
and james you'll have to unmute yourself
again okay
nicholas benjamin hi everybody
um let me find my actually i'll just
i'll just rip it
i like that we got you okay great cool
um so first thank you somewhere
go ahead okay thank you both uh for this
fantastic talk
um your your excitement is infectious
so my my question is what what changes
might be needed in our educational
system in order to popularize i don't
want to use that word but i'm using that
word
um dialectic
whoa um go ahead john
the reason i ask this is because it's
very difficult to engage in dialectic
with anybody i know
um yeah it's just
so i mean this is where the neoplatonic
tradition is very helpful
uh as james argued neil uh dialectic is
the capstone
practice you you you don't you know it's
a practice that
um often we get the sense even in plato
you get a sense this is all kinds of
training
and plato says you can't even start this
until you're 30 years old because you
have to do all this
this training um initially so i i think
that
one of the things i'm trying to do with
peter and and with guy senstalk
and um elizabeth the bold and thomas
steiniger and
all of these amazing people is to try to
figure out is there a way in which we
can set
what i often call an ecology of practice
a sequence uh practices
that will help take people into this uh
can we use something
um you know like you know uh leher's
work on philosophical
companionship to just get people into uh
starting to talk to each other in the
being mode
and then could we could we take them
into circling and or peter's anti-debate
and then could we and then could we put
on top of that
right um also you know individual and
collective mindfulness practices to do
what james and i are just talking about
learning to step back and look at and
learn
be learning just you know to to look
through and then
i think you might have
the proper educational program
for introducing dialectic proper in
and so in fact the neoplatonus even had
a sequence by which you read the
dialogues
that was supposed to take you through
this sort of progression
um um into something like uh dialectic
proper
i would also point out the work of my uh
at least i'm i'm on a stereo right now
on a on a stereo uh podcast
i'll call you tomorrow seven o'clock
so i would want to point to so now we
both got to do it james that's great
yeah
i point to the work of my friend and
colleague zack stein who talks about you
know
education in a time between two worlds
about uh so i think he has
he's very and i've had dia logos with
zach on several occasions
thanks to andrew sweeney and i think
he's very much in concert with what
james and i are talking about and trying
to
reconfigure uh education and make it
more in the service of
the normativity of culture and less in
the service of the normativity of the
market
and to try and build in this kind of
progressive program
where you lead people into this capacity
by building up a scaffolding of skills
that enable it and make it possible you
you've got it john that's actually the
angle that i'm coming from is that zack
stein's book
education and time between worlds there
you go well there you go so
that's not a coincidence i think but i'm
interested to hear what james has to say
well uh the th
this opens the door to
one of my big critiques of the
university which is that
uh it's become dominated by uh
by money by yeah yeah by huge amounts of
money
and and what's happened i you know this
sounds very dramatic
but i'll because we don't have much time
i'm going to make it sound extreme
that is uh essentially what's what's
been happening
is as as the as wealthy donors and
corporations and
major industries contribute to the
university
uh to a higher education and to the
to the learned institutes what we have
is a
is is people who are being
paid actually what they're doing is
buying knowledge
and and what's happening in the uh in
the they determine
what kind of research is being done
what's going to be studied
and what's going to be known uh now
that's that's extremely limiting
and and uh and then on the other hand
the faculty
and i'm really quite critical of my of
my colleagues
uh they're also a bit too much
for sale they're willing to sell their
their
own careers for uh you know for
chairs and for uh extra funds and
so on for high salaries and that's
that's that's a great tragedy and i i
want to
i'm rethinking a whole lot about the way
the university could be restructured
and i'm questioning a number of things
i'm questioning for example
just the the phenomenon of the semester
why why would education be just eight
semesters
long a college education it should last
a lifetime
it should start back in childhood and
continue
all the way to the end and uh and i'm
i'm
i'm worried about the tuition problem
where
um essentially what you do when you pay
tuition is buying knowledge
you're buying you're buying you're
paying someone to teach you
and the more money you have the more
they'll be able to teach you
and that's it's a profound unfairness
and then the third
the third thing is uh admissions to
to colleges um it's become so
uh uh how should i say it's so selective
what we're really doing is now is
creating a kind of intellectual elite
that that basically gives a damn about
the dialectic
uh they're they're they know they don't
care at all about it they're not
dialectical thinkers
and um they're actually what they're
really learning
is not dialogue they're learning
artisanship
uh how to raise how to how to build a
corporation how to raise money how to
invest
and so on and those are those are really
very i think very
very destructive of the uh of the
university of
higher education uh all together which
which in fact the university in my view
is is the is the west's uh
greatest achievement to create the
university
and and now we're we're watching it uh
fall apart
under the impact of uh corporate
interests basically
that's simplistic but it's it's uh it's
on the way to
i mean i i have a much broader critique
but but that's basically the core of it
so james i don't know if you've read him
i i met him at another conference
and we we we we hit it off and had quite
a bit of
discussion in exchange nicholas
maxwell's book from knowledge to wisdom
which is exactly is a critique about the
university along those lines
that you've just made yeah and it's it's
quite a good book
um no thank you i haven't read it i'll
look it up for sure
yeah right right
but uh it it begins in the classroom
necklace
thank you both guy you're up next
hello hey
how are you great to see you man i'm
good i wouldn't miss this one
hi james i'm guy thanks doc nice to meet
you um i first read your book when i was
a
a uh soft sophomore in high
school um and i think yeah
oh yeah it opened i think it opened me
in ways that i'm realizing in this
moment how deeply of an influence it's
had on me
um so i really appreciate what you're
what you're up to
um and how much your body you're
embodying what you're saying
um my question has to do with
actually a moment that you guys had
and it was that moment where john you
were talking about um
reading the the the neoplatonics and
john
just like his toenails like went through
his eyes
and then there was this kind of that's
john in essence
absolutely um and i what
what it looked like to me was a just a
profound
affinity that you guys had for each
other in that moment
that had been growing through the
dialogue that started to feel like
generative of the actual insights in the
dialogue
yeah um and so i'm just curious about
about the connection between what you
think the connection is
between um the personal
the personal aspect of
of what people often only experience in
in like
intimate conversations right like um
personal intimacy
and the the corollary
i don't know what's the correlation
between though that experience the
connection that experience
and the experience of of of intimacy one
experiences
in a philosophical dialogue
um i just i'm fat i'm really
i'm i'm really struck by by whatever
that is because it seems
it just seems very very um
generative of of of the whole project
well my i don't know yeah john
john could answer this too but my own
view is
they should be continuous it is the
uh the personal and the intellectual uh
you don't stop one to start the other uh
you
you should uh being being intellectual
is not a solitary activity it's
it's it's it's a participatory activity
and that's that's uh that's why
there's a kind of sociality there's a
companionship
uh that goes with well with with genuine
intellectuality
it's not being right or wrong it's about
finding ways of continuing the
conversation and uh that's
that can that always involves uh a
person
a deeply personal elements
so i i would agree with that especially
the the continuity hypothesis of the
invocation
of sort of participatory knowing which
is something
some of you know and guy you know i talk
about at length um
and i think i think those that affinity
i think there's a way in which
these are all interpenetrating and into
affording each other
i think my participatory knowing of
myself and my participatory knowing of
others
are not separable things i think and
this is part of what
christopher moore actually argues in his
book on socrates
socratic south knowledge socrates
claimed that only by
examining others did he actually
properly examine himself
and the unexamined life is not worth
living um as he famously said
at his uh at his apology
so i think my participant nor knowing of
myself and my participatory knowing
of the other uh the other person
my community those are bound together
but i think they're also bound together
with the third which is uh
we equally participate in
uh distributed cognition uh and we've
talked about that
already that networking together and i
think
the way we i participated myself i
participate
with my other and then i participate in
the culture
of the just the distributed cognition i
think those are all
interpenetrating and inter-affording and
then the final thing
all of that all of that interpenetrating
recursive
thing going on that is has a
participatory relationship
with the environment right especially
the natural world
and the intelligibility of things the
fact that the world
is an inexhaustible horizon and source
of new intelligibility
and and we are constantly in
participation with that so we
participate
in our ecology in our culture in each
other in ourselves
and all of those participatory knowings
are deeply interpenetrating and
intra-forwarding
and part of what dialectic is about is
about getting that affinity
or you know uh accessed and accentuated
more and more for people yeah very good
you know
i'm glad you brought in the uh
ecological element
always yeah that's part of 40 cognitive
science
yeah thanks god so i
i mean there's much more about this and
you and i have continual deal logos
about it
but that's that that's at least the the
seed of my answer to that
really profound question oh
great oh
david collins you're up next
hi uh first just thanks this is a joy
and um want to push um somewhat unfairly
to hear more about potential downsides
in relevance realization
john is there a potential
for leaving things out to go for
relevance to salient
what we just focus on and somewhat
analogously uh
james with a kind of future oriented
vector
or a growth vector in infinite games
is there any risk of forgetting
where we start from i'm reminded
playfully in the timaeus
um yeah much of learning is about
recovering what we already know or where
we oh yeah
started from thank you
so i guess you mentioned me first so
i'll answer first on this one um
yeah i mean in fact that's always the
case
it's always the case that we're leaving
something out um
that's what i mean about the and and
that's why
we have the experience of insight
insight is it's the experience of that
uh our relevance realization framing has
has
realized that something has been left
out and that it has to restructure
itself
and it self organizes that's so insight
is a powerful
developmental engine of the evolution of
our relevance realization that's why i
study insight
so extensively uh as a cognitive
scientist
so i think that's that's exactly right
uh
i i guess the the the point there
is can we cultivate the proper set of
virtues that stir us between arbitrary
and algorithmic
such that we are always open to
that self-correction because we will
always be in need of it
um and so i was trying to gesture
towards that when i talked about
you know socrates's notion and i think
this does go back to socrates
that wisdom begins in wonder and then
what plato does is try
and uh uh he tries to bring
wonder into awe and then i'm i'm
thinking of woodruff's notion
of reverence as the as the virtue
that uh that we cultivate uh for awe
for wonder and all reverence is the
virtue uh that keeps us
open not just representationally
but in a participatory fashion to um
uh to self-correction precisely because
we
what ah and wonder do is put us in a
place where we are motivated to call
into question
our most comprehensive sense of self and
world and i think
that uh and i agree with woodruff that
the virtue of reverence
uh maybe because it got associated with
uh you know adherence to
particular creeds or dogmatics but the
virtue of
of reverence is a lost virtue in our
culture we we complement
people by saying that they're irreverent
which is actually a kind of
odd thing to do right an irreverent
person somebody who's never capable of
reverence
is deeply somebody who can't call their
view
into question uh via wonder and awe
that they are not trying to matter to
something greater than themselves
and therefore uh given sort of our best
understanding right now
uh they're condemning themselves to a
relatively unexamined life
with very little meaning in life within
it um
and so i think virtues are not
final solutions but virtues are our best
way
of committing to maintaining
a participatory openness to the ongoing
need for self-correction
that's how i would answer that david i
can't
improve on that that's lovely thanks
john well thank you
jim james i think it's really
it's very it's very encouraging uh it's
like to i mean we did meet before but it
was very brief but to to
you've been in my thoughts for a very
long time and it's very nice
to find such affinity and consonants
with him
i i it's it's very philia for me i'm
very very much enjoying oh
good good yeah me too
so yeah time for about two more
questions
uh joe uh you had a question
about ai
yeah so it was kind of a broad question
but i was just wondering if either of
you could riff on what it would
look like or mean for ai to play
the infinite game well
i mean maybe james will let me go first
on that because that is my wheelhouse as
a cognitive scientist
i do a lot of work on ai especially
artificial general intelligence
um so here's a brief answer but
it it actually encompasses every i i
think in a very
at least at a stems to encompass
everything james and i've been talking
about i think
for an ai to be able to play an infinite
game and to also be
generally artificially general
intelligence is it has to be capable of
relevance realization in the way i've
been talking about it and that is
precisely
the thing that we are having so much
difficulty in giving
our our artificial intelligence we can
now we're starting to make some progress
on it precisely because
we are starting to if you look at you
know hinton way back to 96
and the wake sleep algorithm and all the
work building on that what we're seeing
is
and and they they sort of fell into this
is that what you have is you have you
know a dynamically self-organizing
system
right like implemented on a neural
network
and what it does is it sort of
implements exactly what i'm talking
about it introduces variation
and then puts selection on it and then
varies from that and so it's constantly
evolving
it's fittedness now i'm not saying the
wake sleep algorithm is
the the the answer but the reason why
deep learning is precisely so successful
and we've had this
amazing burst of work in ai is precisely
because
i think they are now turning to and this
was dreifus's critique
way back when on what computers can't do
they're turning to the problem of
relevance
and they're making it central and
they're seeing that a dynamical
evolution of sort of ongoing constraint
on the problem space
is exactly what's needed to make
something general intelligent
and i think if we give it that ability
um then we will have
ai that can play infinite games as
opposed to just finite games
yeah i more or less agree i'm i i i'm a
kind of
hold out on on ai i'm not
first place i i'm not that familiar with
the literature but but
um but i have such a respect for
uh how shall i say this the
uh the kind of uh i'm looking
for a word that the kind of fungibility
of language
that that it it it so easily falls apart
and and evolves and changes and that
the edges the edges get mushy
and so on and this happens in a in a
social context
that that probably will never be
predictable
uh in in any way so that that
even though it's extremely useful and
and
and uh can do uh extraordinary things i
mean i've seen it
i've seen it do amazing stuff um
i'm i'm holding out on it's its absolute
relevance in the end
i could be convinced but i'm still um
i i would say that um i think the pro
maybe this will
i don't think it'll completely close the
gap between us but i've argued that the
project of just
trying to create artificial intelligence
is a misplaced project
because the degree and this is already
happening the degree to which we make
these things
capable of a self-organized evolving
fittedness is the degree to which like
us they become subject to self-deceptive
uh behavior and so we also need
artificial
uh uh to give them artificial
rationality that's sort of going up
but also going down um so far a
cognitive science says that you know you
only have
the kind of mind you have because you
have the kind of body you have the
living body you have this is an
aristotelian argument which is now come
back into prominence
and so i think that artificial
intelligence has to have conjoined with
it
both artificial relevance sorry
artificial rationality as the
ability to deal with self-deception and
artificial life
the thing the the the the the machine
well it won't be a machine anymore in
some senses
the machine has to be like what we are
it has to things have to be matter to it
precisely because it's
it has to take care of itself um it it
constantly has to be making itself the
way we are
um the way living things are and
i mean reid montague says you know the
difference between us and computers is
they don't care about the information
they're processing
and we do and i would argue that we care
about it precisely because we're
always every moment to moment taking
care of ourselves and each other
and i think if we don't give that as a
fundamental
uh you know cons constitutive structure
of these machines that they will never
approach our kind of cognitive agency
amen yeah
all right so we'll sneak in this last
question from michael
uh about lifelong uh learning if you can
unmute yourself mike
yes hello my question was
what is the next step of lifelong
learning if we can't use
turn to universities in their current
form
i know you've been talking to tomasz
bjorkman and
here in sweden and i'm going to be a big
fan of you both and a friend of thomas
erin
what is like the wisdom gym you're doing
here at the store is one part of it but
but how do you scale that up what what
is the conversation in your parts james
and john
on lifelong learning how do we actually
go to a society that can
that can transcend the current system in
learning like
is it how are we going to talk for 10
more years are there any projects or
experiments going on
right now that's that uh
it's a tough question um
you um i i would put it very simply this
way
start one rather than look for one
begin to engage your friends talk to
them
uh in in a in a way bring bring the
dialectic
into uh your your social and
and personal in in personal life
and i you know you know what i think you
if you did
and you probably do anyway i can tell
from the way you you framed your
question
if you if you did you'd find there are
all kinds of
of co compatible social as
compatible human beings uh around you
uh and and uh i i just think it needs to
be
sort of consciously pursued uh by
by individuals uh i i i
wish i had a a better solution for it
but
uh but you you know it's it's
actually it's the reason i went in i
became a teacher
i i wanted to engage in dialogue with uh
with uh my fellow human beings and
i found teaching a way to do that you
don't have to be a teacher
but but uh that's one one way of doing
it
so james oh sorry james go ahead you're
good
no well i agree with james and i've
actually been trying to do that i've
been i
i so uh as some of you know i have an
online uh meditation and contemplation
cultivation of wisdom
uh uh thing i do every morning live
stream 9 30
right and a sangha has grown up around
that
and then that senior is situated within
a discord server which so you get the
nesting of communities
um so i i've i've been doing the what
james said
um uh building helping to build one of
those
or cultivate maybe is a better word
helping to cultivate one of those and
also be a teacher within it
uh but what i've also been doing um is
i've been
trying to meet up and do participant
observation
and to have deep discussion with other
such communities
uh the emer these immunitarian
communities of practices
that seem to be doing dialectic around
religio
if you'll allow me a bit of a slogan and
there's a lot of them
and i was just at the movement summit a
couple weeks ago with rafe kelly and i
was just impressed
by all all of these you know growing
communities of ecologies of practices
that are
responsible responding to the meeting
crisis by
very much by doing that you know uh
and and what's also impressive is the
degree to which they're
uh talking to each other um and
not in the sense of trying to crush or
conquer
but much more in a sense of creating
something like a wiki
or a co-op uh structure between them and
so i often talk about um that
what's happening is in these movements
is a blurring of the line between
michael between education and
enculturation
um and i used to be quite pessimistic
this is why i ended up doing something
like awakening from the meeting crisis
uh because i i i saw
the the a lot of the cultural machinery
as
uh frustrating and crushing people's
projects of trying to
enhance uh meaning in life and cultivate
wisdom but
i'm more optimistic i i think there's
that's why i did that slogan a few times
a few weeks ago in the store with akira
the dawn of about uh
you know stealing the culture in the
sense of not trying to
create some sort of political revolution
but do something like what happened in
the axo revolution
or you know or or or the rise of
christianity within
um the the roman empire or
or james's uh model of the renaissance
in
in infinite games right it's not it's
not political at least in
the posterity sense it's a way of
basically
opening up and recreating and
reconnecting culture
in a way that is subversive of the way
in which our culture is locking us into
a kind of finite mode
finite game having mode and a and and
a binding of education to the
normativity of the market
as this exclusive uh normativity so i
see
um you can you can definitely
create a community you can join a
community and you can also help
facilitate the community the the growth
of the community of communities
uh that makes a a new culture
come into existence um now are we gonna
do it
in our lifetime well i hope we do enough
of it in our lifetime that we can save
the planet
uh because that's very urgent but will
we well
i mean this this kind of project is is
it's like the medieval project of
building a cathedral
you commit to something that is going to
be cross-generational not just
uh within your own life so i hope we do
enough
now that we uh we we we
avoid extinction not only of ourselves
but of many species
uh but i also ask people to
be willing once again to commit to the
long-term project of culture
the way they have in the past
yeah yes
so i just wanna quickly mention that
there is a project in trondheim city
that we're working on called lifelong
the learning society project that is
actually a couple to four u.n
organizations that we just started this
year
[Music]
anyone want to connect with me about
that you're welcome as well
oh oh good i i would like to know about
that thank you
so we reached our any any final words
from uh you gentlemen before we close
out for the day
oh thank you thank you and thanks thanks
john i i really enjoyed
it yeah good yeah
me too james i i really enjoyed this
um and it's
um it's always i always feel welcome
here
at the stoa and so thank you for that
peter and uh
um if you would like to james i would be
happy to do this again
at some point in the future i found this
very very
beneficial and nourishing and so i'd be
happy to do it again
yeah i would too excellent okay
so i'll make some uh closing
announcements related announcements to
the talk that just happened here uh
before
i do that uh on behalf of the whole stoa
family in the store village that's for
me here
john james infinite gratitude and and
thanks uh your way
for that wonderful talk which will be on
youtube i'll probably post it uh
tomorrow so um before i talk about
upcoming events we have one in an hour
uh sign up to the sub stack and go to a
support uh store on patreon if you like
talks like this
and we also have a discord now everyone
was asking for it so there it is
um so in an hour uh our very own tyson
wagner is interviewing another tyson
that's very very relevant to what
was spoken about today um tyson could
you plug that event
yes thank you tyson yonkoporta author of
sand
talk how indigenous thinking can save
the world speaking of saving the planet
he will be here at 8 30 eastern time
um giving a talk and doing a q a and i
know that
at least like seven or so people i know
personally from this community
uh read the book um it's an incredible
book and so i look forward to seeing
some of you there
and also here at the stoa i am procuring
a space
for joyful play on mondays called
flowing with unknowingness where we get
to explore
freestyle self-expression and dialogue
through
rap in the spoken word and next week
that will be at 8 45
immediately following daniel
schmuckenberger's event on
monday so i'll see you all soon thank
you
and thank you tyson and john if you want
an experimental
way to get into communitas definitely
visit the freestyle
rap that tyson hosts here this though
it's freaking incredible um you can rcp
there the links are in the chat uh david
collins you have an event
this thursday would you like to speak on
that sure
um looking forward to especially after
tonight
um adam robert over the side of you and
i will be
having a discussion uh focusing on
ways in which socrates practice is a
kind of
example of an inspiration for um
contemplative practice tonight we talked
a bit about
understanding plato through the
neoplateness i come through the zen
tradition
and the western uh apophatics the cloud
of unknowing
in order to understand the neoplatonists
in order to understand plato and and
socrates kind of got it started
with his claim not to know and
invitation
to uh have us examine what means most to
us
david is that going to be recorded um
i'll send you the article too john uh
his article is really good
i would really like that i would really
like that thank you very much
and uh the last event it's tomorrow at
that i'll plug it's at 6
30 p.m uh as john mentioned a sort of
authentic dialogue wii space type
movement uh
donna rodriguez who's the kind of the
resident stoa space practitioner
she's uh having a session called
intersubjective partner meditation
that's at 6 30 pm eastern time i think
you'd really like this one john it's a
different sort of modality that
i don't think you've uh experimented
with yet but donna's really really knows
what she's doing
so that could be found uh right here um
so yeah there's there's so many freaking
events at the store i can list them all
but uh
check out the website and uh yeah thank
you so much for everyone
coming up today
you